A Finding Aid to the Stanton Macdonald-Wright papers, 1907-1973, in the Archives of American Art AAA.macdstan
Archives of American Art
Stanton Macdonald-Wright papers
1907-1973
AAA.macdstan
Archives of American Art
3.1 Linear feet
The papers of Southern California painter Stanton Macdonald-Wright measure 3.1 linear feet and date from 1907 to 1973. The collection contains correspondence with family, friends, and artists, including Morgan Russell, and his wife Suzanne Binon, Michel and Suzanne Seuplor, Ann and John Summerfield, and Bethany Wilson. Also found are writings, six diaries, travel journals, printed materials, and artwork.
Macdonald-Wright, Stanton, 1890-1973
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 5 series.
Series 1: Correspondence, circa 1907-circa 1972 (0.5 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Writings, 1920-circa 1970 (0.9 linear feet; Box 1-2)
Series 3: Diaries, 1909-1973 (1.3 linear feet; Box 2-3)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1913-1967 (0.3 linear feet; Box 3, OV 4)
Series 5: Artwork, 1969 (0.1 linear feet; Box 3, OV 4)
Biographical/Historical note
Stanton Macdonald-Wright (1890-1973) was the creator of a modernist style of painting based on pure spectral color known as chromatic abstraction or "Synchromism." He worked in New York and later primarily in Los Angeles.
Stanton Macdonald-Wright was born in 1890 in Charlottesville, Virginia. In 1900 the family moved to Santa Monica, California where they ran a seaside hotel. A few years later he took courses at the Art Students League in Los Angeles, studying under Warren T. Huges. His older brother was Willard Huntington Wright, a respected art critic who wrote Modern Painting: Its Tendency and Meaning (1915), upon which he collaborated with his younger brother Stanton, and The Future of Painting (1923), and later became a detective novelist under the name S. S. Van Dine.
At the age of seventeen, Stanton Macdonald-Wright married his first wife and moved to Paris where he immersed himself in European art and studied at the Sorbonne, the Académie Julian, the École des Beaux-Arts, and the Académie Colarossi. While in Europe he also befriended fellow American painter Morgan Russell and the two artists began working closely together. They studied with Canadian painter Percyval Tudor-Hart between 1911 and 1913 and were deeply influenced by their teacher's color theory, which connected the qualities of color to those of music. Together Macdonald-Wright and Russell developed a style of painting based on color and named it "Synchromism." They introduced their work in 1913 at the Der Neue Kuntsalon in Munich and in Paris at the Galerie Bernheim-Jeune. These exhibitions helped to establish Synchromism as an major influence in modern art well into the 1920s.
Stanton Macdonald-Wright and Morgan Russell returned to the United States eager to promote their work and theory. It was not long before the two separated, but both continued to work in the Synchromist style. Together, they held one more Synchromist exhibition in New York in 1916 which received significant critical support. Macdonald-Wright also participated in the prestigious 1916 "Forum Exhibition of Modern American Painters" in New York and exhibited his work at Alfred Stieglitz's famed 291 gallery in New York in 1917. Yet, financial success evaded him.
Macdonald-Wright moved to Santa Monica in 1918, where he taught and served as director of the Los Angeles Art Students League. In 1924 he published his instructive Treatise on Color. In 1927 he organized another joint exhibition with Morgan Russell at the Los Angeles County Museum of Art, where he also exhibited five years later. He exhibited at the Oakland Art Gallery, the California Palace of the Legion of Honor in San Francisco, Alfred Stieglitz's An American Place gallery in New York, and the Stendahl Galleries in Los Angeles. From 1935 to 1942 Macdonald-Wright served as director of the Works Progress Administration's Federal Art Project for Southern California, followed by a faculty position at the University of Southern California at Los Angeles where he taught for sixteen years.
In the late 1950s, Macdonald-Wright completed the Synchome Kineidoscope, a color and light projecting machine first envisioned by Macdonald-Wright and Morgan Russell as early as 1913.
Macdonald-Wright traveled extensively throughout the 1960s and early 1970s, spending time in Hawaii, Italy, and Japan. Macdonald-Wright married three times and died in California in 1973, at the age of 83.
This biographical note draws heavily on the Archives of American Art's West Coast Regional Collector Paul Karlstrom's collection description written upon acquisition of the papers.
Conditions Governing Access note
ACCESS RESTRICTED; use requires written permission. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Existence and Location of Copies note
Portions of the collection are available on 35 mm microfilm reels LA1 and LA5 at Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The bulk of the Stanton Macdonald-Wright papers were donated to the Archives of American Art by his widow, Jean Macdonald-Wright, in 2 installments in 1995. The artist's unpublished autobiography was donated to the Archives by gallery owner David Nellis in 1978.
Related Archival Materials note
The Archives of American Art holds several collections related to the Stanton Macdonald-Wright papers. There is an oral interview of Stanton Macdonald-Wright conducted 1964 Apr. 13-Sept. 16, by Betty Hoag. There are also Stanton Macdonald-Wright Letters to Alan and Fanny Leslie, the Stanton Macdonald-Wright Collection of photographs, Stanton Macdonald-Wright Letters to Morgan Russell, Walter Houk Letters from Stanton Macdonald-Wright, and an Oral History of Stanton Macdonald-Wright by Jeanne M. Marshall for the Voice of America Conducted in 1967.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of Southern California painter Stanton Macdonald-Wright measure 3.1 linear feet and date from 1907 to 1973. The collection contains correspondence with family, friends, and artists, including Morgan Russell, and his wife Suzanne Binon, Michel and Suzanne Seuphor, Ann and John Summerfield, and Bethany Wilson. Also found are writings, six diaries, travel diaries, printed materials, and artwork.
Writings consist of drafts of essays, plays, and book manuscripts. There are drafts of A Treatise on Color with palettes and color wheels, The Basis of Culture, and Macdonald-Wright's autobiography Bittersweet: An Artist's Life.
There are six diaries and numerous travel journals. One diary was written in Paris in 1909 in which Macdonald-Wright muses over the aesthetics of art and his color theories. Five additional disbound diaries cover his life from 1939-1973. Travel diaries date from 1959-1972 and cover trips to Italy, Japan, and Hawaii.
Printed material includes a copy of Les Synchromistes exhibition catalog, a newspaper clipping, and The Future of Painting by Willard Wright. Artwork consists of blueprints for Macdonald-Wright's Synchrome Kineidoscope, a color and light projecting machine first envisioned by Macdonald-Wright and Morgan Russell as early as 1913 and finally completed in the late 1950s.
Separated Materials note
Materials microfilmed on reel LA1 and LA5 were loaned to the Archives of American Art in 1964 and returned to Stanton Macdonald-Wright after microfilming. They include a brochure on the Santa Monica Library murals and six photographs of the panels while in Macdonald-Wright's studio. There is also a 1939 exhibition catalog for "Southern California Art Project" a master's thesis on Macdonald-Wright by Dori Jean Watson (1957), and one scrapbook of photographs, clippings, and other printed materials dating from circa 1910-1964.
Russell, Morgan, 1886-1953; Seuphor, Michel, 1901-; Summerfield, Anne, 1917-; Summerfield, John, 1917-; Blueprints; Color in art; Diaries; Essays; Hawaii--Description and travel; Italy--Description and travel; Japan--Description and travel; Mural painting and decoration, American--California--Santa Monica; Painters--California--Los Angeles; Painting, Abstract; Synchromism (Art); Travel diaries
- Correspondence, circa 1907-circa 1972; Series 1; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists of personal correspondence with family, friends, and fellow artists. Family correspondence is comprised of letters from Stanton Macdonald-Wright and his brother Willard to their parents describing their difficulties during wartime in London as they establish their careers. There is one folder of letters originally labeled "Willard 1913-1915" (now labelled "from Willard") among the early family correspondence to Macdonald-Wright's parents, but since the letters are signed under various pseudonyms, it is difficult to know for certain which brother is writing. Other correspondents include Morgan Russell and his wife Suzanne Binon, Michel and Suzanne Seuphor, Ann and John Summerfield, and Bethany Wilson. Unless otherwise noted, the bulk of the correspondence consists of outgoing letters written by Macdonald-Wright to various recipients.
  Arrangement note
  Family letters to Macdonald-Wright's parents are at the start of the series. The rest of the correspondence is arranged alphabetically. Undated and miscellaneous correspondence is grouped together at the end of the series.
  - Family Correspondence - Wright, Archibald and Annie, circa 1907-1914 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Family Correspondence - Wright, Archibald and Annie, 1909-1913 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Family Correspondence - Wright, Archibald and Annie (letters from Willard), 1913-1915 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Barthoux, Jules (letters from), 1958-circa 1963 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Russell, Morgan and Suzanne (Binon), circa 1953-circa 1955 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Seuphor, Michel and Suzanne (letters from), 1954-1957 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Seuphor, Michel and Suzanne (letters from), 1958-1966 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Summerfield, Anne and John, circa 1965-circa 1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Wilson, Bethany, circa 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Wilson, Bethany, circa 1963-circa 1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Wilson, Bethany, circa 1963-circa 1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Wilson, Bethany, circa 1963-circa 1967 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Wilson, Bethany, circa 1963-circa 1967 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Wilson, Bethany, circa 1963-circa 1967 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Wilson, Bethany, circa 1963-circa 1967 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, circa 1942-1968 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Writings, 1920-circa 1970; Series 2; 0.9 Linear feet Box 1-2
  Writings consist of typescript and handwritten drafts of essays, plays, and manuscripts by Stanton Macdonald-Wright. This series includes an untitled manuscript for a novel loosely based on the lives of Stanton and his brother Willard, essays on art, and a notebook of haikus. There are also drafts of A Treatise on Color with palettes and color wheels; The Basis of Culture, a survey of art around the world; and Bittersweet: An Artist's Life, a copy of Macdonald-Wright's unpublished autobiography.
  This series is organized chronologically.
  - Handwritten Draft of Untitled Manuscript, circa 1920-circa 1950 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Typescript Draft of Untitled Manuscript, circa 1920-circa 1950 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "The Rebirth of the Classical Impulse", 1920 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "Four Fantastic Satires", circa 1922 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Includes only 3 of the 4 plays.
  - Essays on Art, circa 1922-circa 1925 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - A Treatise on Color, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Color Wheels and Charts, circa 1924 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Color Wheels and Charts, circa 1924 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - "The Structure of Art", circa 1930 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - A Basis of Culture Glossary and Notes, circa 1933 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - A Basis of Culture Byzantine and Italy Chapter, circa 1933 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - A Basis of Culture Modernist Art Chapter, circa 1933 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - A Basis of Culture Persia Chapter, circa 1933 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - A Basis of Culture Mesopotamian Races Chapter, circa 1933 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - A Basis of Culture Etruscan, Greco-Roman, and Roman Art Chapter, circa 1933 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - A Basis of Culture The Italian Renaissance Chapter, circa 1933 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - A Basis of Culture Revision Notes, circa 1933 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Haiku Notebook, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Bittersweet: An Artist's Life, circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bittersweet: An Artist's Life, circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bittersweet: An Artist's Life, circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Diaries, 1909-1973; Series 3; 1.3 Linear feet Box 2-3
  This series includes Macdonald-Wright's extensive diaries. There is one small bound diary from his time in Paris. The disbound diaries, originally in 5 binders, span over three decades and document the artist's experiences in California, excluding his trips abroad. The travel diaries were written on hotel stationary and notebooks during Macdonald-Wright's numerous trips to Hawaii, Japan, and Europe. Prior to their arrival at the archives, portions of the diaries were edited and some pages have sections cut out and repasted on different pages.
  The disbound diaries and travel diaries are grouped separately and arranged chronologically within each grouping. The disbound diaries were originally received in five large binders with pages numbered from 1-1502. These pages were removed from the binders and placed in folders arranged by date. The travel diaries come after the disbound diaries.
  - Paris Diary, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Disbound Diary 1, 1939 January-March (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Disbound Diary 1, 1939 March-April (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Disbound Diary 1, 1939 April-December (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Disbound Diary 1, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Disbound Diary 1, 1941-1943 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Disbound Diary 1, 1955 December (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Disbound Diary 1, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Disbound Diary 1, 1957 January-April (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Disbound Diary 2, 1957 April-August (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Disbound Diary 2, 1957 August-December (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Disbound Diary 2, 1958 January-May (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Disbound Diary 2, 1958 August-December (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Disbound Diary 2, 1959 January-July (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Disbound Diary 2, 1959 January-July (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Disbound Diary 3, 1959 July-December (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Disbound Diary 3, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Disbound Diary 3, 1961 January-October (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Disbound Diary 3, 1961 October-1962 September (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Disbound Diary 4, 1963 April-October (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Disbound Diary 4, 1964 April-September (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Disbound Diary 4, 1965 September-1966 January (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Disbound Diary 4, 1966 June-October (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Disbound Diary 4, 1967 June-December (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Disbound Diary 4 Miscellaneous Writings, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Includes miscellaneous "observations" from 1967 and 1968 grouped together at the end of the disbound diary 4 entries.
  - Disbound Diary 5, 1968 January-April (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Disbound Diary 5, 1968 May-August (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Disbound Diary 5, 1968 November-1969 March (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Disbound Diary 5, 1969 June-August (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Disbound Diary 5, 1969 November-1970 March (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Disbound Diary 5, 1970 June-August (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Disbound Diary 5, 1970 October-1971 April (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Disbound Diary 5, 1971 May-September (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Disbound Diary 5, 1971 October-1972 February (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Disbound Diary 5, 1972 April-July (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Disbound Diary 5, 1972 September-1973 August (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Hawaii and Japan Travel Diary, 1959 May-June (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Japan Travel Diary, 1960 March-August (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Japan Travel Diary, 1960 September-November (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Hawaii and Japan Travel Diary, 1961 April-July (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Japan Travel Diary, 1962 March-June (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Japan Travel Diary, 1962 October-1963 April (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Japan Travel Diary, 1963 October-1964 April (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Japan and Los Angeles Travel Diary, 1964 November-1965 August (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Hawaii and Japan Travel Diary, 1966 January-1967 June (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Japan Travel Diary, 1967 September-November (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Japan Travel Diary, 1968 May (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Italy Travel Diary, 1968 September-November (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Japan Travel Diary, 1969 March-May (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - France, Italy, and England Travel Diary, 1969 August-November (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Italy and London Travel Diary, 1970 April-May (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Japan Travel Diary, 1970 September-October (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Japan Travel Diary, 1971 April-May (Box 3, Folder 26)
    Includes a personal essay titled "Summation at Eighty."
  - France and Italy Travel Diary, 1971 September-October (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Hawaii Travel Diary, 1972 February-April (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Hawaii Travel Diary, 1972 July-September (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Printed Material, 1913-1967; Series 4; 0.3 Linear feet Box 3, OV 4
  Printed material consists of one complete copy and one partial copy of the exhibition catalog Les Synchromistes: Morgan Russell et Stanton Macdonald-Wright Exposition, 1913, a photocopy of a newspaper clipping, and a hardbound book The Future of Painting by Willard Wright.
  - Les Synchromistes: Morgan Russell et S. Macdonald-Wright Exposition, 1913 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - The Future of Painting by Willard Huntington Wright, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - "The Manifeste des Pintres du Groupe: Les Artistes Musicalistes", 1932 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    Oversized material housed in OV 4.
  - Newspaper Clipping, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Oversized French Manifesto from Box 3, Folder 32 (Box OV 4)
- Artwork, 1969; Series 5; 0.1 Linear feet Box 3, OV 4
  Artwork consists of blueprints for Macdonald-Wright's Synchrome Kineidoscope, a color and light projecting machine that involved multiple projectors and film.
  - Kineidoscope Blueprints, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Oversized Kineidoscope Blueprints from Box 3, Folder 34, 1969 (Box OV 4)